The Type of Problem that we will go
over is Molar volume and combine it with
molecular formulas and empirical formulas.
These are always the toughest
problems because they combine
old concepts with gas laws.
So if you remember from older videos,
older chapters that you've covered
in your course, one thing is that
a compound has, can be labeled as
percents, meaning that we can figure
out exactly what the chemical makeup is.
But we don't know what
the molecular formula is.
So I have a compound
here that's made of 24.
018 percent mass carbon and 75.
982 percent fluorine.
Now with percents, that can give us
the empirical formula, which was the
simplest ratio of your molecular formula.
It's not the true identity, but
it gives you the simplest ratio.
Now if you have 1.
55 grams of your compound
and it occupies 0.
174 liters at SDP, what
is the molecular formula?
Now the bottom piece of information,
what that tells us is it gives us
an identity of what the molecule is.
Bye.
So we can actually figure out what the
molecular mass is from that, but we can't
figure out what the actual formula is.
So with the percent, you can figure
out the formula for the empirical,
and down here you can find out
what your molecular mass is.
So if you kind of remember back,
flip through your notes, you'll
see, Oh crap, that is actually
setting you up for your problem.
Let's go through the steps of
how to do this kind of problem
first before we go through it.
And if you'd like to write them down
as you go through it, it'll help you be
able to follow along with this video.
If this is your first time seeing
empirical formula problems.
I would recommend my empirical formula
video to help you be able to do that,
and you can see the link is below in
the, in the about section of the video.
So the first thing we have to do is we
need to find and set up the problem like
an empirical formula problem, meaning this
is where we're going to use our gas laws.
So in the problem here, it's
at STP, meaning we're going
to use the molar volume.
It's going to be an easier problem,
but sometimes you have to use
the ideal gas law to find that.
So it allows you to find the
number of moles, which you
can then plug into the mass.
So mass divided by moles
is your molar mass.
So if you're given a mass in a
problem and all of the different
ideal gas values, you're going to
have to go through these steps.
So that will give us our molar mass.
Now from there, what we will
do is go through our steps of
an empirical formula problem.
The first thing is, is being that
you were given percents, remember
the word per cent, out of 100.
So, what we assume is a 100 gram sample
per percents of our empirical formula.
So we will convert those to grams.
Then our goal is always the mole,
meaning we will go from gram
to mole of each of our units.
So we had carbon and
fluorine in this problem.
Thank you.
We will convert both of those to moles.
And what you're going to see
is there's going to be a mole
to mole ratio between them.
And being with molecules, we're
always interested in what the smallest
ratio is because that illustrates
what the true percentage is.
So whichever is the smaller of the
two, you'll divide both by that.
And then that will give you your
different, uh, subscripts for your values.
So let's say if we were to divide that,
and if we had some kind of species,
We'll just say from there we had, um,
uh, A, B3 was, let's say, our subscripts.
So it's like, well, what
would I do from there?
Well, if that's your empirical
formula, this is where you'd
go on to the next part.
So step five is optional depending on
what you were given in the problem.
In this case, you had the gas
law information, so you can,
you have to continue, right?
You're not done.
Oh, sad days, right?
You have to keep going.
So if that's the case, well, depending
on, being that you have this problem,
you found the molar mass from part one.
So what you'll do is you'll, with
that, let's say that AB3 molecule,
you'll find the empirical mass,
and now you will divide the two.
So when you divide the bigger one,
which is the molecular mass, by the
empirical, you're going to gain a ratio.
So now the purpose of that whole
number ratio, so if you get a decimal,
that means you divided it wrong.
You got you to flip the two numbers.
This is going to be the number
that you're going to use to
multiply your empirical formula by.
So let's say if I had a b three from
earlier and I got a ratio of three,
You would multiply that formula by 3
to then get A3B9, which could be your
hypothetical molecular formula, which
is, should match your gas law molar mass.
Alright, so this is what we're
going to go through in this problem.
It looks a little complicated right
now, but I would recommend writing
these steps down for yourself.
So if you want to pause it,
rewind, and write them down.
Then it will help you be able to follow
along with the video, especially if
you're trying to do this for yourself.
If you learn how to do it for, let's say,
your homework or for an exam, um, and
this is you, this is a common problem
that you can see maybe in introductory
chemistry or in general chemistry.
Let's take a look at how we do it.
Let's start with actually just finding
what our molecular formula is, and then
we can kind of put this guy in, it's
not a normal empirical formula problem.
We'll be using our gas laws first.
So earlier, we did this step
where we found out what the moles
were for using the ideal gas law.
We could still do that here,
but there's another ratio that's
important to know when you are at STP.
So when we are there, what
that means is Is that 22.
4 liters of any gas is
equivalent to one mole at STP.
Okay, so being that this problem is here,
that makes the problem faster and easier.
So being that we have 0.
174 liters here, we can convert
this to moles using this value.
So what we'll do is we'll put 22.
4 liters on the bottom, that's equivalent
to 1 mole, and we will use this to cancel
out our liters, and we will have how
many moles are in this molecular formula.
So when we do that, we will get
0077678 moles of our unknown gas,
and we're not sure what it is.
Now to figure out our molar mass,
well if you keep in mind, we
gotta do grams divided by moles.
So we were given 1.
55 grams earlier, so let's find
out what our molar mass is.
So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to take that 1.
55 grams and then I'm going to
divide it by the number of moles
that we have, that we just obtained.
Okay, so I'll put that down here, we'll
divide those two values, And what that's
going to give us is our molar mass.
So by doing these and combining
them together, you'll get 199.
54 grams per mole.
So this is your molecular mass.
So great.
Now what we're not on, unfortunately,
there's a little bit more, and
this is taking stuff that we
went over during moles, right?
So taking that concept of empirical
formulas, empirical masses.
which are your ratios.
So if we find the empirical formula,
we can find what its molar mass is, and
then divide it into this guy to figure
out, well, what's the ratio that you
need, multiply it by to get your formula.
So earlier we were given this
bit of information about the
mass and, uh, of molecules.
Carbon and fluorine.
We can use this to do our next step.
We can assume that this is a hundred
grand out of a hundred grams, so
we'll take 24.018 and we'll also
take our mass of fluorine as well.
So we'll color code.
So we have 24.018 or
75.982 grams of fluorine.
We have our number for carbon and
we are going to convert them both.
Moles.
So now when we do that, we are
then gonna divide them both
by the lowest number of moles.
They're the least common, or
least common multiple of the two.
So we know that the molar
mass of carbon is one mole.
That's 12.011 grams of carbon from
your periodic, periodic table.
We have fluorine, which is
one molar fluorine equivalent
to 18.998 grams of fluorine.
And when you solve for both of these.
You'll get 1.
999 moles of carbon, and then 3.
999 moles of fluorine.
Now what?
We gotta divide by what the
least common multiple is.
So which, what's the smallest of the two?
We're gonna divide by
carbon, because it's smaller.
So when we divide both of these by 1.
999, we're gonna get our empirical
formula, which is going to be C1F2.
Now, what we can do with this value
is figure out what the empirical mass
is, because we want to divide it into
that molar mass that we had earlier.
So, in order to find that,
we will take that 12.
011 grams per mole, and add that times
the molar mass of fluorine, and what we
are going to get is a molar mass of 50.
07 grams per mole.
We're going to take this and divide
it into the mass we had earlier.
So we had 199.
and we will divide 50.
07 into that number and this is
going to be the ratio which is 4.
So we'll take 4 times it by c f2
and your final molecular formula
is going to be c, c4 at 8.
And that's how you can combine moles,
empirical formulas, gas laws, And
put everything together, right?
So this is probably the hardest problem
you could ever have when it comes to
these because it combines old concepts
with new concepts and helps you be
able to figure out exactly how to
figure out all these hidden steps.
I hope this video helped.
I know it was a longer one, but it goes
through all the tips and tricks of how to
solve those really hard gas law problems.
Thank you so much for listening, and I
hope to all see you in the future, and if
you haven't yet, please hit that like and
subscribe button, and please check out my
other videos on gas laws to help you fully
master your understanding of this concept.
Um, also feel free to go to
the empirical formula video to
understand this part as well.
Thank you all, and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.